Hello my friends, how are you doing?
안녕하세요, 여러분 잘 지내시죠?
Today I want to take you on a journey that is probably going to change your life.
오늘은 여러분의 삶을 바꿀 여정을 함께 떠나보려 합니다.
We are going to have a lot of fun with ConfUI and I'm going
ComfyUI를 아주 재밌게 다뤄볼 건데요.
to show you why it is so capable and such an amazing tool.
정말 놀라운 도구인 이유를 보여드리죠.
I want you to imagine ConfUI as a canvas on which you doodle.
ComfyUI를 여러분이 낙서하는 캔버스라고 생각해보세요.
Imagine yourself as a kid and you just draw out anything that is in your mind,
어린 시절처럼 마음속에 떠오르는 모든 것을 그려내는 거죠.
in your fantasy because ConfUI is absolutely adaptable and open.
ComfyUI는 개방적이고 적응력이 정말 뛰어나니까요.
So in this video, in this lesson, we're going to talk about the basic
이번 영상에서는 기본 기능과
functionality and how to understand it and create in an easy and fun way.
쉽고 재밌게 이해하고 활용하는 방법에 대해 이야기할 겁니다.
Here we have a very simple work flow that is just creating this very nice image here.
여기 아주 멋진 이미지를 만드는 간단한 워크플로우가 있습니다.
You can see here there's different elements in here and we have here these
여러 요소들이 있고, 서로 연결된 선들이 보이시죠?
lines that are connecting everything together.
이것을 함께 만들어 볼 건데요.
So we're going to build that together but before we do
그전에 인터페이스가 어떻게
that I'm going to show you how the interface itself works.
작동하는지 먼저 보여드리겠습니다.
So let's start fresh here with this element.
여기 이 요소부터 시작해 보죠.
You can move that around any way you want it on the screen.
원하는 대로 화면에서 이동할 수 있습니다.
Here you have several controls in there and there might be something you don't have.
여기 여러 컨트롤들이 있는데 없는 것도 있을 수 있습니다.
This is the manager and that is very important because here you can install all
이것은 매니저인데 아주 중요합니다.
of the custom nodes which are these little boxes we have just seen.
여기서 우리가 방금 본 작은 상자 같은 커스텀 노드를 설치할 수 있죠.
Now this is very very easy to install.
설치는 매우 간단합니다.
You need to go to the github page of the CompFUI manager and then you want to
ComfyUI 매니저의 깃허브 페이지로 가서 조금 아래로 스크롤하면
scroll down a little bit... and here you see this text line..
이 텍스트 줄이 보일 겁니다.
Git clone and then the web address of the CompFUI manager.
'Git clone'과 ComfyUI 매니저 웹 주소입니다.
You want to select all of that and copy that.
이걸 모두 선택해서 복사하세요.
Then you're going to go into your CompFUI Windows Portable folder.
다음으로 ComfyUI 윈도우 포터블 폴더로 가세요.
In there in the CompFUI folder... in there into the custom nodes folder.
ComfyUI 폴더 안의 custom_nodes 폴더로 들어가세요.
And when you're here you want to click up here in the address bar and type This is
여기서 주소 표시줄을 클릭하고 cmd를 입력하면 명령 창이 열립니다.
going to open up your command window and
명령 창이 열리면
here you simply paste what you copied before.
복사한 텍스트를 붙여 넣으세요.
Now that the text is in here, you simply hit
텍스트가 입력되면 엔터를 치고
enter and wait for it to finish downloading.
다운로드가 완료될 때까지 기다립니다.
It should only take a couple of seconds.
몇 초밖에 안 걸릴 겁니다.
After you've done that, you can close the command window and you're going to click
완료되면 명령 창을 닫고 ComfyUI 윈도우 포터블 폴더에서
here in the confui windows portable folder again on run nvidia gpu bat.
run_nvidia_gpu.bat을 다시 클릭하세요.
This is going to start confui for you and is
ComfyUI가 실행되고 매니저
finishing the installation of the manager.
설치가 완료될 겁니다.
Once you have that and you see this button here, click on that and you will see this.
이 버튼이 생기면 클릭해서 이 화면을 볼 수 있습니다.
There's a lot of different buttons in here but they are all easy to understand.
여기 여러 버튼들이 있지만 이해하기는 쉬울 겁니다.
There are three buttons that are very important for you.
여기서 중요한 세 가지 버튼이 있습니다.
One is the update all button.
첫 번째는 'Update all' 버튼입니다.
And over here you might get a message that your confui is outdated.
ComfyUI가 구 버전이라는 메시지가 표시될 수 있는데
So you can click on that and wait for it to finish.
클릭하고 완료될 때까지 기다리세요.
This will update confui and all of the custom nodes that you have installed.
ComfyUI와 설치한 모든 커스텀 노드를 업데이트할 겁니다.
The second one The last one that is very important
두 번째, 마지막으로 중요한
for you is the install custom notes button here.
것은 'Install Custom nodes' 버튼입니다.
You can click on that and this is going to open up a list for you.
클릭하면 목록이 나타납니다.
You can see on the right side when you already have installed
오른쪽에서 이미 설치한 노드를
notes, you can either disable them or uninstall them.
비활성화하거나 제거할 수 있습니다.
Disabling might be useful when they are conflicting with other custom notes.
다른 커스텀 노드와 충돌이 생기면 비활성화하는 게 유용할 수 있습니다.
And of course you also have an install button so you can go and install it from here.
물론 설치 버튼도 있어서 여기서 바로 설치할 수도 있습니다.
You don't even have to go to the GitHub page anymore.
더 이상 깃허브 페이지에 갈 필요도 없죠.
Now here are some of the note packs that I want to suggest to you.
다음은 제가 추천하는 노드 팩입니다.
One is called the confui impact pack.
첫 번째는 ComfyUI Impact 팩입니다.
The other one confui inspire pack.
두 번째는 ComfyUI Inspire 팩이고요.
The efficiency notes for confui, the ultimate SD upscale
세 번째는 ComfyUI 효율성 노드, 네 번째는 Ultimate SD Upscale,
and then also the confui confi roll custom notes.
마지막으로 ComfyUI Confy Roll 커스텀 노드입니다.
Because these have some of the most used custom notes in them.
가장 많이 사용되는 커스텀 노드가 포함되어 있습니다.
Another thing you might want to do in here is to install models.
모델을 설치하는 방법도 있습니다.
When you click on that you will have here a list of models.
클릭하면 모델 목록이 나올 겁니다.
Now you will realize that these are often not models
이 모델들이 이미지 생성에 직접 사용하는 모델은 아닐 겁니다.
that you are using for image generation itself.
대부분 업스케일러 모델이죠.
For example up here this one for example is very good.
예를 들어 이 모델은 매우 좋습니다.
The 4x foolhardy remakri.
4x Foolhardy Remacri 모델이죠.
The 4x ultra sharp is also very good.
4x Ultra Sharp도 매우 좋습니다.
The 8x nmkd super scale 150,000 g also very good.
8x NMKD Super Scale 150,000 G 모델도 매우 좋습니다.
And you can actually see on the left side by the type what it is.
왼쪽에서 유형별로 확인할 수 있습니다.
Now you see here we have upscale, inside face, face
업스케일, 얼굴 복원, 체크포인트,
restore, we have checkpoints, we have embeddings and so on.
임베딩 등이 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
Don't be too much concerned about that right now.
지금은 너무 걱정하지 마세요.
We don't need all of that at this moment.
지금 당장은 다 필요하지 않습니다.
Before we get started you might want to do one more thing.
시작하기 전에 하나 더 할 일이 있습니다.
You will find the file extra model paths yaml example.
extra_model_paths.yaml.example 파일을 찾으세요.
Now you want to delete the dot example part at the end so it's becoming a yaml file.
끝에 있는 '.example'을 지워서 yaml 파일로 만드세요.
And then you can open this up.
그리고 파일을 여세요.
Personally I'm using for that the notepad plus plus software
저는 메모장++을 사용하지만
but you can use any kind of text editor if you want to.
다른 텍스트 편집기를 사용해도 됩니다.
Now if you already have for example automatic 11.11 installed what you want to
Automatic 1111이 이미 설치되어 있다면 'base_path'를 Automatic
do is to set the base path to your automatic 11.11 and in there to the web ui
1111의 webui 폴더로 설정하면 다른 폴더들을 자동으로 연결합니다.
folder and then this will automatically link to
구조가 같기 때문에 자동으로
these other folders here with the same structure.
하위 폴더들을 연결할 수 있습니다.
So that means it loads all of the models that you have from automatic 11.
Automatic 1111 모델들을 하드 드라이브에 복사할 필요 없이
11 without having them as a duplicate on your hard drive.
ComfyUI에서 그대로 불러올 수 있죠.
You want to save that and you can close all of that and then you can click in the
저장하고 모두 닫은 다음 메뉴에서 'Refresh'를 클릭해서 모델을 로드하거나
menu here on refresh so it's loading all of the models or alternatively you can
또는 ComfyUI를 다시 시작해서 모든 모델이 로드되는지 확인하세요.
simply restart comfui if you want to make sure that everything is loading correctly.
이제 노드를 찾고 생성하는 방법을 알아볼까요?
Now where do we find the nodes and where do we create that?
여기서 한 가지 팁을 드리자면 마우스 휠로 확대, 축소할 수 있는데
Here is one advice I want to give you.
이때 주변에 파란 선이 보일 겁니다.
You can zoom in and out with your mouse wheel and when you do
이것이 캔버스의 시작 영역입니다.
so you will realize there's a very thin blue line around here.
작업을 시작할 때 모든 요소가 파란 선 안에 있는지 확인하세요.
Now this is the starting area of your canvas so when you start to build make
파란 선을 넘어가도 되지만, 핵심 워크플로우는 이 사각형 안에 있어야
sure that everything is inside of that blue line.
다음번에 워크플로우를 로드할 때 정상적으로 로드될 겁니다.
You can go over the blue line but the core of your work flow should be inside of that
다음으로 노드를 추가해야겠죠.
blue rectangle here because next time you load your
이 파란 사각형 안쪽에서요.
work flow it's loading that area of the work flow.
워크플로우 영역을 로드하기 때문이죠.
Next of course we want to add some nodes in here.
이제 노드를 추가해 보겠습니다.
The easiest way to do this is to double click on the canvas.
캔버스를 더블 클릭하는 것이 가장 쉽습니다.
This is going to give you this search window.
검색 창이 나타날 겁니다.
Here you can see you can scroll through all of the nodes.
여기서 모든 노드를 스크롤할 수 있죠.
But even better you can type up here what you want to have for example understand
더 좋은 것은 검색창에 원하는 노드를 입력하는 겁니다.
this is for creating the images.
예를 들어 케이스 샘플러는
Now we want to click on that and you can see this is adding the node for us.
이미지를 생성하는 노드입니다.
So this is super simple and of course you need to know the name of the node but over
클릭하면 이렇게 노드가 추가됩니다. 정말 간단하죠.
time because Because you, in most cases, use the same notes, you will remember the
물론 노드 이름을 알아야 하지만 대부분 같은 노드를 사용하기 때문에
names over time, or you can look them up in other
시간이 지나면 이름을 기억할 겁니다.
work flows or ask in the Discord communities for ConfUI.
다른 워크플로우를 참고하거나 ComfyUI 디스코드 커뮤니티에서 물어보세요.
So in here you see we have some inputs here for the model, positive prompt,
여기 모델, 긍정 프롬프트, 부정 프롬프트 입력이 있습니다.
negative prompt, the latent image, which is the latent
그리고 레이턴트 이미지, 즉 레이턴트 노이즈나
noise or anything you want to input as a latent image.
레이턴트 이미지로 입력하고 싶은 것들이 있습니다.
And then we have some settings here, like the seed number.
다음으로 시드 번호 같은 설정이 있습니다.
You want to have here maybe randomizing the seed, but you can also choose here
시드를 랜덤으로 설정하거나 여기서 선택할 수 있습니다.
from these pop down menus, for example, have a fixed seed for every generation,
예를 들어 항상 같은 시드를 쓰거나 증가, 감소시키도록 할 수 있죠.
the same seed or increment or decrement.
즉, 매번 같은 시드나, 증감 시킬 수 있죠.
Increment means it goes up one number, decrement means it goes down one number.
증가는 1씩 증가, 감소는 1씩 감소하는 것을 의미합니다.
So you can see in these choices here, we have different kind of data inputs.
여기서 선택하는 데이터 입력값이 다릅니다.
Here we have a pop down menu, while here we have a number.
여기서는 드롭다운 메뉴를 사용하고 여기는 숫자를 입력해야 합니다.
These are full numbers with no decimal point.
소수점 없는 정수만 입력 가능하죠.
And down here for the CFG, for example, we do have
CFG 같은 경우 소수점을 입력할 수
numbers where you can have a decimal point in there.
있는 숫자를 입력해야 합니다.
So these are called floats and these are called integer numbers.
이것을 '플로트'라고 하고 이건 '정수'라고 부릅니다.
Then you have a sampler in here.
다음으로 샘플러가 있습니다.
You see it's a long list.
목록이 아주 길죠.
There's also a filter here where you can search for what you want to use.
여기서 필터로 원하는 것을 검색할 수 있습니다.
And then below that, you have a scheduler.
그리고 아래에 스케줄러가 있습니다.
Now, this is something you don't have in Automatic 11.11.
Automatic 1111에는 없는 기능입니다.
And this here actually gives you more freedom.
여기서 더 많은 자유를 얻을 수 있습니다.
First of all, you can see there's more schedulers in
먼저 스케줄러가 더 많을 뿐 아니라
here, but then also you can combine them any way you want.
원하는 대로 조합할 수 있습니다.
So, for example, when you go in here and you have, for example, DPM++ SDE,
예를 들어 여기서 DPM++ SDE를 선택하면 케라스 버전이 없는데,
there is no Keras version because you select this
이걸 선택하고 케라스는 여기서
and then separately you select Keras in here.
따로 선택해야 하기 때문입니다.
So this gives you more combination, more abilities for experimentation.
그래서 조합을 더 많이 할 수 있고 실험할 수 있는 여지도 더 많아지죠.
Below that, we have the denoise that is similar to image to image rendering.
아래에는 이미지-이미지 렌더링과 유사한 디노이즈 설정이 있습니다.
So basically, in any step in COM4UI, you can do
기본적으로 ComfyUI의 모든 단계에서 유연하게 이미지-이미지를
image to image because you want to be more flexible.
처리할 수 있도록 자유도를 더 높인 것입니다.
You have a lot more ability inside of COM4UI.
ComfyUI에서 할 수 있는 일이 훨씬 많죠.
Now, how about these connection points here?
그럼 이 연결 지점들은 뭘까요?
On the left side, you will always have the inputs.
왼쪽은 항상 입력 부분입니다.
On the right side, you will always have the outputs.
오른쪽은 항상 출력 부분이고요.
When you click and drag, this is turning into one of
클릭해서 드래그하면 국수 가닥 모양의 선이 생기는데,
these noodles or cables and you can let go of them.
선을 놓으면 연결할 만한 노드를 추천해 줄 겁니다.
And this will suggest to you something that might be useful to connect.
또는 여기서 검색을 클릭해서 다른 노드를 검색할 수도 있습니다.
You can also click here on search to have the search
또 다른 중요 기능은 'reroute'입니다.
window again if you want to search for something else.
이 기능은 정말 유용하게 쓰이죠.
Another functionality that you have in here that
자주 사용되는 중요한 기능인데요.
is often very important is called the reroute.
바로 리라우트(reroute)입니다.
Now, this gives you this little element here.
이 작은 요소가 나타납니다.
Now, the interesting thing, let's move this over here is I can, for example,
흥미로운 것은, 예를 들어 이걸 이쪽으로 옮기고 리라우트
let's create a little bit more reroutes here and pretend that
노드를 더 만들어서 이게 다른 노드 라고 가정해 봅시다.
these are other nodes that we are using for other things.
다른 용도로 사용한다고 가정을 해봅시다.
Now, let's say I have another case sampler down here.
그리고 또 다른 케이스 샘플러가 아래에 있다고 해보죠.
Let's simply copy that down here.
그냥 이걸 아래로 복사해 볼까요?
And I want to reconnect all of these to the
이 모든 것을 첫 번째 케이스 샘플러 대신
second case sampler instead of the first one.
두 번째에 연결하고 싶다고 가정합시다.
Instead of going through all of them, I can simply
하나하나 연결하는 대신에
go now like this and I've switched everything.
이렇게 하면 모두 바꿀 수 있죠.
So that is very useful.
정말 편리한 기능입니다.
But there is also a second important purpose for these reroute nodes.
리라우트 노드에는 또 다른 중요한 목적이 있습니다.
This can give you a lot more clarity in your work flow.
워크플로우를 더 명확하게 만들 수 있죠.
So let's say, for example, the cable runs like this.
예를 들어 케이블이 이렇게 연결되어 있고
And I have a node sitting here like that.
노드가 여기 이렇게 있다고 해보죠.
So this is going behind the node and it might
이 선이 노드 뒤로 지나가서 어떤
get very confusing of what's actually happening.
일이 일어나는지 헷갈릴 수 있습니다.
So instead, you can use these reroute nodes to have
이럴 때 리라우트 노드를 이용해서
this go around that and by that creating more clarity.
이렇게 둘러가게 하면 더 명확해지죠.
Now, there's also another reason for using these reroute nodes, and that is to make
리라우트 노드를 사용하는 또 다른 이유는 워크플로우를 더 깔끔하고
your work flow cleaner and easier to understand.
이해하기 쉽게 만들기 위해서입니다.
So, for example, here you can see we have a lot of cables that go all over the place.
예를 들어 여기저기 흩어진 케이블이 많이 보이죠?
This can become very visually cluttered.
시각적으로 매우 복잡해 보일 수 있습니다.
So instead, we can use this reroute node to put it simply closer to it.
대신 리라우트 노드를 이용해서 가까운 곳에 배치할 수 있습니다.
And by that, we have only one cable going over here while
그렇게 하면 하나의 케이블만 여기로 지나가고 다른 것들은
the others simply go to the other nodes in a shorter path.
더 짧은 경로로 다른 노드로 연결될 수 있게 됩니다.
And this makes it much easier to understand.
이해하기가 훨씬 쉬워집니다.
Now, let's have another look at our starting node
이제 시작 노드를 다시 한번 볼까요?
here because there's a lot more you can do with that.
더 많은 것을 할 수 있으니까요.
You can see here on the left side we only have four
여기 왼쪽에는 4가지 입력이 있고
different inputs and then all of these choices.
아래에는 여러 선택지가 있습니다.
But what if you want to have, for example, the seat being controlled from the outside?
만약 시드를 외부에서 제어하고 싶다면 어떻게 해야 할까요?
An example for that could be that you're using multiple case samplers, but you want
예를 들어 여러 케이스 샘플러를 사용하는데 모두 같은 시드를
to use the same seat in each of these case samplers.
사용하고 싶을 때가 있을 수 있습니다.
So for that, what you could do here is right click.
그럴 땐 여기를 우클릭해 보세요.
And then down here you have a selection of convert seat to input.
여기서 'Convert seed to input'을 선택할 수 있습니다.
So all of these controls can be converted to input.
여기 있는 모든 컨트롤을 입력으로 변환할 수 있습니다.
So when I click on that, you can see that now
클릭하면 시드 설정이 없어지고
the seat is gone and I have an input for that.
입력 부분이 생긴 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
I can now create a seed node and connect that.
이제 시드 노드를 만들어서 연결할 수 있습니다.
And as I said before, here we have now two
앞서 말했듯이 이제 두 개의 케이스
case samplers that are fed by the same seed.
샘플러가 같은 시드를 공유하게 되었습니다.
So when this is randomized, it is creating one randomized
무작위화하면 하나의 무작위 숫자를 생성해서
number that then is going out to both of these case samples.
두 케이스 샘플러에 보내게 됩니다.
So both of them always use the same seed number and that can be very helpful.
둘 다 항상 같은 시드 번호를 사용하게 되는 거죠. 아주 유용합니다.
If you no longer need that input, you can
더 이상 입력이 필요 없으면
always right click again and then set this back.
다시 우클릭해서 되돌릴 수 있습니다.
So down here you see convert seed to widget.
여기서 'Convert seed to widget'을 선택하세요.
So when you click on that, this is removing the input and now you have here
입력이 제거되고 케이스 샘플러 안에 설정이 다시 나타납니다.
the setting again inside of the case sampler.
다시 설정이 내부에 생성됩니다.
There's also more things you can do to customize your node.
노드를 커스터마이징하는 방법이 더 있습니다.
For example, you can change the title up here.
예를 들어 여기 제목을 바꿀 수 있습니다.
For that, right click, go to title and then in here you can add something.
우클릭해서 'Title'로 가서 원하는 이름을 입력할 수 있습니다.
Now I would suggest to you to keep the
원래 이름을 유지하고 뒤에
original name and then add something behind it.
추가하는 것을 추천합니다.
For example, let's say anime.
예를 들어 'anime'라고 해보죠.
So this is for example the case sampler for the anime style that we want to create
이것은 우리가 만들고 싶은 애니메이션 스타일의
so that you know what kind of node it is and also what it is for.
케이스 샘플러라는 것을 알 수 있도록요. 무슨 노드인지, 왜 쓰는지 알 수 있게 말이죠.
This is important so you have clarity over what is happening and why you're using it,
특히 며칠, 몇 주 뒤에 워크플로우를 다시 볼 때 무엇을 위한 노드인지 알 수 있도록요.
especially when you come back to your work flow days or weeks later.
무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지 명확하게 하는 것이 중요합니다.
Another thing you can do to create more visual
시각적으로 더 명확하게 만들려면
clarity is to change the color of your node.
노드의 색깔을 바꿀 수 있습니다.
So you right click again.
다시 우클릭해 보세요.
You can see here we have color.
여기 'Color'가 보이죠?
And with that, for example, I can change this to green.
예를 들어 초록색으로 바꿀 수 있습니다.
And you could, for example, switch all of your case samplers over to green.
그리고 모든 케이스 샘플러를 초록색으로 바꿀 수도 있습니다.
So when you look at your work flow, you know
그렇게 하면 워크플로우를 볼 때
exactly where all of the case sampler nodes are.
모든 케이스 샘플러 노드가 어디 있는지 정확히 알 수 있습니다.
Another thing you can do to stay better organized is to create groups of nodes.
정리하는 또 다른 방법은 노드 그룹을 만드는 것입니다.
For that, you want to right click on the canvas and then select add group.
캔버스에서 우클릭하고 'Add Group'을 선택하세요.
This will give you a colored box.
색깔이 있는 상자가 생길 겁니다.
I often put this above my nodes and then you can drag this out over all of the nodes.
저는 보통 노드 위에 배치해서 노드를 모두 덮습니다.
If you want, you can make it a little bit shorter and then move the nodes inside.
필요하다면 좀 더 짧게 만들어서 노드를 안으로 이동할 수 있습니다.
Now this gives you an area that now combines all of
이제 이 그룹 안에서 모든 노드를
them together so you can move them around together.
함께 이동하거나 조작할 수 있습니다.
You can also bypass all of them together.
모두 함께 우회시킬 수도 있습니다.
So you can right click here and then select bypass group nodes.
여기서 우클릭하고 'Bypass group nodes'를 선택하세요.
Everything is going to turn Violet.
모두 보라색으로 변할 겁니다.
This means it's bypassed.
이는 우회되었다는 뜻입니다.
It's not being used at the moment.
현재 사용되지 않고 있는 거죠.
And you can undo that by again right clicking
다시 우클릭하고 'Set group nodes to all nodes'를
and then select set group nodes to all nodes.
선택해서 다시 활성화할 수 있습니다.
Like this.
이렇게요.
Now here's a fair warning.
여기서 주의할 점이 있습니다.
This is a sticky area.
이것은 끈적거리는 영역입니다.
So that means if you move this area over any other node, even if you only touch it
이 영역을 다른 노드 위에 조금이라도 올려놓으면 노드 그룹의 일부가 됩니다.
a little bit, it will become part of the nodes.
아주 조금만 닿아도 그룹에 포함됩니다.
You have to be a little bit careful where you're putting your groups.
그룹을 배치할 때 조금 조심해야 합니다.
And if something sticks to it, you can simply move it out of the way.
무언가가 달라붙으면 그냥 옮겨서 빼내면 됩니다.
And then it's outside of the group again.
그럼 다시 그룹에서 분리됩니다.
Also for any individual node, you can also bypass them.
개별 노드도 우회시킬 수 있습니다.
You do that by right clicking on the individual node.
개별 노드를 우클릭하면 됩니다.
And then select bypass.
그리고 'Bypass'를 선택하세요.
And if you want to reactivate them again, right click on the node.
다시 활성화하려면 노드를 우클릭한 다음
And in this case, also select bypass.
여기서 다시 'Bypass'를 선택하세요.
And this will activate them again.
그러면 다시 활성화됩니다.
This also works for nodes inside of groups.
그룹 안의 노드에도 적용됩니다.
So you can turn off individual nodes inside of a group.
그룹 안의 개별 노드를 끌 수도 있죠.
Thanks for watching and check out my next lesson.
시청해 주셔서 감사하고 다음 강의도 기대해주세요.
Oh, you're still here.
아, 아직 안 가셨네요.
So this is the end screen.
이제 엔딩 화면입니다.
There's other stuff you can watch like this or that's really cool.
이런 영상도 있고, 아주 멋진 영상들도 있습니다.
And yeah, I hope I see you next time.
네, 다음에 또 만났으면 좋겠습니다.
I'll see you soon.
곧 만나요.
Leave a like if you haven't yet.
아직 좋아요 안 눌렀으면 눌러주세요.
And well, yeah.
네, 그럼 다음에 뵙겠습니다.